本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流
更多中日双语字幕，尽在www.kamigami.org 及微博@诸神字幕组
日听&翻译
小伍
sora
兰樱
校对
小江
mam
大陸公路の中心に位置する強国パルス
Mighty kingdom of Parsa in the center of the continental way.
片源
Rei
时间轴
钦钦&框框
压制
久嘉
Coolkid
いまだ何も知らず　何者でもない王子
Inconspicuous prince who has nothing does not know.
しかし　彼は後に王と呼ばれることになる
But in due time, he will become king.
その者の名は　アルスラーン
And his name Arslan.
Chapter last
The era of pars, 320 a year.
パルス暦３２０年
パルスの豊かな領土を狙い　異教徒の国　ルシタニアが侵攻を開始
Lyusitaniya, following a belief,
launched an invasion to capture a prosperous Pars.
Maru
Atropatene
Parsee
パルス王　アンドラゴラス三世は自ら軍を率い　ルシタニアを迎え撃つ
King Parsis, Andragoras III of,
personally I led an army against Lyusitanii.
王太子アルスラーン　初陣
Prince Arslan came to the battle
The heir to the throne of the kingdom of Pars, Arslan
時に１４歳
in fourteen years.
圧倒的に有利と思われたアトロパテネにおける大戦は
The Great Battle of Atropatena
It was supposed to end in their favor,
カーラーンの裏切りにより　累々たるパルス軍の屍を積み重ねた
but, because of the treachery of Harlan,
completed countless casualties among the soldiers Parsis.
華々しく飾られるはずであった初陣は
The first fight, which was supposed to be amazing,
It turned into a living hell.
さながら地獄となった
Traitor, captain of cavalry, Harlan
カーラーン　なぜだ
Harlan, why ?!
故あってのことです
So there were circumstances.
悲しく　あわれな王子よ
The poor and the wretched Prince,
敵襲
Attack!
殿下
Prince!
ダリューン
Darjun!
Captain of Cavalry of the kingdom Pars, Daryun
I came to save you, Prince!
今　お助けいたします　殿下
Wait here a little bit.
しばしそこでお待ちください
このダリューンがお守りいたしますゆえ
I Daryun, will protect you.
I rely on you, Daryun.
後は任せた　ダリューン
待て　ダリューン　話を聞け
Wait, Daryun! Listen to me.
What are you saying?!
今更　何を言う
国王陛下を裏切り　王太子殿下にこのようなまねを
Betraying His Majesty the King
and the Crown Prince, do you dare ...
Wait a minute! If you know the reason you will not even blame ...
待て　事情を知れば　お主とて　俺の行為を責めは…
ここは一旦退くぞ
We retreat!
カーラーン
Harlan!
同日　夕刻を前にして
On the same day, when dusk fell back,
無敗を誇ったアンドラゴラス三世率いるパルス軍は　大敗を喫した
proud invincible army under the leadership of Parsis Andragorasa III
He suffered a crushing defeat.
Eighteenth kingdom pars ruler Andragoras III
蛮族どもめが
To these barbarians!
ダリューン　殿下をお守りいたせ
Daryun, Baby Prince.
陛下
Your Majesty!
General wage kingdom Lyusitaniya, Mr. Silver Mask
敗残の老いぼれが　出過ぎたまねをするな
Defeated a fool, do not stick your nose where you are powerless!
そやつを王などと呼ぶな
Do not call him king.
お前は何者だ
Who are you?
これほどの憎しみを受けながら　私が誰かも分からぬほど
You - the subject of fierce hatred,
but you do not even know who I am.
悪行を重ねてきたか
How much evil you have done!
Sixteen years...
１６年…
この日が来るのを１６年間待ち続けたぞ
I waited for this day sixteen years,
アンドラゴラス
Andragoras!
殿下　私の後ろを離れないでください
Prince, please do not go very far from me.
It's okay. Shabrang understands.
大丈夫だ　シャブラングが理解してくれている
My father stepped ?!
父上は退却したのか　王都へ
In the capital?
早く王都に戻らなければ
You need to get back to the capital.
しかし　王都へ戻るには　このまま戦場を突っ切らねばなりません
But to get back to
we will have to cross the battlefield.
マルズバーンたちがこれほど倒されているということは
If so many people from marzban killed
on the way to the capital city can be full of soldiers Lyusitanii.
王都までの道はルシタニア兵であふれ返っていると思われます
そうか…
Clear...
我が友　ナルサスを頼りましょう
Enlisted the help of my friend Narsusu.
ナルサスとは　いつぞやのお主が言っていた　ひねくれ者の友か
And this Narsus ...
This is your wayward one, which was discussed?
はい　元ダイラムの領主でございました
Yes.
Once he was the ruler of Daylama.
聞いたことがある　父上によって宮廷を追放されたと
I heard about it.
Father removed him from the court.
数年前　三国同盟が我が国に侵入した折
A few years ago,
When in our alliance invaded kingdoms troyh kingdoms
兵を一人も使わずに　敵軍を退散させた男です
He shoved the enemy,
do not go into battle any soldier.
He will meet with me, son of a king?
王の息子の私に会ってくれるだろうか…
そこはそれ　幸いというのも妙ですが　このありさま
Perhaps the country will call it luck,
but in our position ...
ひねくれ者ゆえ　我々惨めな敗残者を拒みはしません
Let him and wayward,
but he will not give up the conquered people, like us.
惨めな敗残者…
The defeated people ...
今日のところはもうどうしようもございません
Today we do not do anything.
後日　国王陛下と共に復讐戦を挑み　敵を討ちましょう
Later we together with His Majesty will surely find
way to get revenge.
今は生きてこそでございます
And now
we need to survive.
ナルサスは絵が好きなのか
Narsus love to draw?
Well...
まあ…　誰にでも欠点はあるものでして
We all have our weaknesses.
あの男は　天行の運行　異国の地理　暦史の変化
He knows about the movement of celestial bodies,
the geography of the land, the course of history ...
なんでも知らぬことはございません
There is nothing he does not know.
ですが　たった一つ　自分の絵の技量についてだけは
There is only one ...
With regard to skills as an artist,
いわゆる　下手の横好き…
it can be called a mountain enthusiast.
Elam, is that you ?!
エラムか　俺はダリューンだ
It Daryun!
お前のご主人に会いに来た　ここを通してもらえぬか
I have come to see your master!
Not propustysh us?
これは…　ダリューン様
Wow ... Mr. Daryun!
お久しぶりでございます
How many years have passed!
Servant Narsusa, Elam
知らぬこととはいえ　失礼をいたしました
Although I do not know, but I'm sorry for being rude.
ナルサス　俺だ　ダリューンだ
Narsus, it's me, Daryun!
名乗る必要はない　騒々しいヤツめ
Can not predstavlyatsya, screamer.
Former governor Daylama, Narsus
お主の声は１ファルサングも遠くから聞こえておったぞ
I have long heard your voice.
アトロパテネで我が軍は惨敗したのだな
Our army fell under Atropatena?
カーラーンが裏切った
Harlan betrayed us.
ダリューン
Daryun, thank you for the flattery,
せっかくだが　今更　浮世と縁を持つ気はない
but now I do not want to communicate with global issues.
しかし　山奥で下手な絵を描き散らしているより　はるかにましだろう
But it's better than be locked somewhere in the mountains with lousy pictures!
この男を信用なさってはいけませんぞ　殿下
Do not trust this man, Prince!
こいつは「マルダーン・フ・マルダーン」で物の道理もよくわきまえておりますが
He Fu Mardan Mardan, also with a head on his shoulders.
芸術を理解する心を持ちません
That's just not quite able to appreciate art!
What art ?! You're ...
何が芸術だ　お主のは…
芸術は永遠　興亡は一瞬
Art is eternal! Changes - are fleeting!
エラム
Elam.
おはようございます　殿下
Good morning, Prince.
May I ask one question?
一つ聞かせてくれぬか
エラムの両親は奴隷から解放されたのだったな
Your parents were slaves, but they were released, right?
はい
Yes.
When the previous governor, Mr. Theos died,
前領主テオス様がお亡くなりになり
ナルサス様が相続なされたときのことです
Mr. Narsus became heir.
全ての奴隷を解放してくださいました
He then freed all the slaves.
ならば　自由の身であろう
So you're a free man.
なぜいつまでもナルサスのもとにおるのだ
Why still sluzhysh Narsusu?
私の意志でおそばにおります
I'm staying with him on their own.
人は皆　平等だ
All people are equal!
やはり　奴隷は解放すべきなのだろうか
So, you need to free the slaves?
ご自分でお考えなさいませ
Think about this question for yourself.
私からも頼む
I'm also going to ask.
Please help me with Daryunom.
ダリューンと共に　私を助けてくれ
ありがたいお言葉ですが…
Thank you for saying this, but ...
では　こうしよう
Then so.
私はお主の忠誠を求める代わりに　十分な代償を支払う
In return for your loyalty, I'll pay you handsomely.
私がルシタニアを追い払い　パルスの国王になった暁には…
As soon as we will repulse Lyusitanii, and I'm the king of Parsa ...
ナルサス卿　お主を宮廷画家として迎えよう
Mr. Narsus, I will appoint you a painter in the palace!
なっ
I like you!
気に入った
分かりました
Good.
I Narsus,
このナルサス　アルスラーン殿下にお仕えいたします
I will serve you, Prince Arslan.
ありがとう　ナルサス
Thank Narsus.
そうと決まれば　早々に出立しよう
Once everything has been decided, we go.
ダメだ　門が…
Useless! The gates! ..
Stands before the gates! Do not let anyone!
門の前で固めろ　侵入を許すな
パルス暦３２０年１１月
The era of Pars, November 320 years.
王都エクバターナ　陥落
The capital of Ecbatana fell.
国王アンドラゴラスの生死も不明のまま
The fate of King Andragorasa is still unknown,
パルスは混乱の闇に落ちた
Pars and plunged into the darkness of chaos.
一方　アトロパテネでの敗戦の報を受けたミスラ神殿の神官　ファランギースは
Meanwhile, the terrible defeat at Atropatena
I learned the priestess of the temple of Mithras, Farangis.
Rica temple Mitra, Farangis
旅の楽士　ギーブと共に　アルスラーン一行との合流を果たし
Together with a traveling musician Gievom
Wandering musician Giev
she joined a group of Arslan,
to repulse the haunting of their general-perebezchiku Harlan.
一行を追う裏切りの将　カーラーンの軍勢を迎え撃つ
Atropatene
Royal capital of Ecbatana
We catch the traitor Harlan
これから　裏切り者のカーラーンを捕らえて
アルスラーン殿下のもとへ連れていく
and move to the Prince Arslan.
人手が増えるのはありがたいことだ
Additional strength is to be welcomed.
今　殿下にお仕えしているのは何人か
How many people are currently prince?
俺と俺のレータク　それに天下無双の騎士１人
My servant, I
and one skilled knight.
そして　お主らを入れて　５人になった
And with you there will be only five.
５人…ね
Five, right? ..
いたぞ　崖の上
There he is!
At the top of the cliff!
カーラーン
Harlan, I'm here!
私なら　ここだ
これ以上　罪のない人を殺めること　見過ごすわけにはいかぬ
I will not stand by and watch you kill innocent people!
アルスラーン
Lions!
カーラーン お主に尋ねたい
Harlan, I want to ask you.
マルズバーンとして…　いや
Marzʙana ...
No. As the knight of the kingdom Pars ...
それ以前から　パルスの騎士として
Nobody even behind your back bad word did not say.
誰にも後ろ指をさされたことがないお主が
なぜ　ルシタニアなどに膝を屈したのか
Why do you bow to Lyusitaniey ?!
欲に釣られたとも思えぬ
I do not believe you mastered greed.
理由があるなら　ぜひ教えてくれ
If there is a reason, tell it to me!
知らぬがお主のためだ
You better not to know for your own sake.
Consider me, Harlan, vile traitor, and die,
このカーラーンを醜悪な裏切り者と信じて死んでいくがいい
アンドラゴラスの呪われた子よ
Andragorasa unfortunate son!
なっ
貴様の相手はこの俺だ　カーラーン
I am your enemy, Harlan!
ダリューン
Darjun!
You punk! Know the location!
青二才が　つけあがるな
背中　取った
Back!
Opened!
まだだ　まだ
No! That's not all!
カーラーン
Harlan!
カーラーン　王はどこにおられる
Where is the king ?!
王は…生きておる…
King alive.
Royal capital of Ecbatana, dungeon
Andragoras.
アンドラゴラスよ
Eighteenth kingdom pars ruler Andragoras III
俺が誰だか分かるか
Do you know who I am?
教えてやろう
I'll tell you.
聞き覚えのない名ではないはずだ
This name should be familiar to you.
俺の名はヒルメス
I called Hermes.
My father - Osroes.
父はオスロエスだ
ヒルメス
Hermes...
Right. Hermes.
そうだ　ヒルメスだ
先王オスロエスの嫡子で　貴様の甥だ
Heir Osroesa, the previous king, and your nephew.
そして　パルスの真の国王だ
AND...
True king Parsis.
Royal capital of Ecbatana
Atropatene
王は生きている
King was alive.
After learning about it from Harlan,
カーラーンから新たな情報を得て
Daryun Narsus and entered the royal capital.
ダリューンとナルサスは王都へと潜入した
I heard that a man is looking for something here.
何事か　探っている者がいると聞いてな
ダリューン　教えてやろう
Daryun, I have something to tell you.
貴様の伯父ヴァフリーズを殺ったのは　この俺だ
Your uncle was killed Vahriza me!
なっ
アンドラゴラスの飼い犬めがそれにふさわしい報いを受けたわ
This dog Andragorasa.
He got what he deserved!
貴様の死にざまも伯父に倣うか
And you follow out his uncle ?!
おのれ　ダリューン
やけど
Burn?
ここは一旦退いた方がよさそうだな
It looks like we better yet back off.
Yes, agreed.
ああ　そうだな
エクバターナへの潜入を果たし
Infiltrating in Ecbatana
アンドラゴラス王とタハミーネ王妃の生存の感触を得た
and knew that the king and queen Andragoras Tahameney probably alive
ナルサスとダリューンは再びアルスラーン王子のもとへ戻った
Narsus Daryun and again returned to Prince Arslan.
Be that as it may, we have very few people.
いずれにしても　我々は少数すぎる
How do we find allies?
どうやって味方を増やせばいい
それには　殿下が将来
You, Prince, announced to the people Parsis,
今までの国政において　条理に合わぬことをなくすと
that in the future you will be scattered all the chaos,
パルスの民にお示しになるのです
who now reigned in the kingdom.
First, it specifies that wants to make a prince.
まずは殿下の目指されるものを明らかになさいませ
And we will do our best to fulfill it.
それがかなうように　我らは努力させていただきます
アルスラーンは王都を奪還するため
To return to the royal capital,
パルスの最大戦力を残しているペシャワールを目指す
Arslan went to Peshavard, which remained most of the Parsis forces.
Royal capital of Ecbatana
道中　追撃を振り払うため　カシャーン城塞へと身を寄せたアルスラーンは
Along the way, avoiding enemies chase
Arslan had found refuge in the fortress of Kashan.
城塞の主　ホディーの醜い企みを打ち砕き　奴隷たちを解放する
There the owner of the fortress, Hodir, trying to fool his vile intrigues and Arslan freed slaves.
しかし　奴隷らは逆上
But slaves were furious.
根深い人間の性を知り　困惑するのであった
When he learned that people are accustomed to such a system, he was surprised.
Kashan castle
ダリューン　ナルサス　その他　殿下のおそばにあって
Daryun, Narsus and your other wards,
The owner of the fortress of Kashan, Hodir
able to harm you ...
殿下の害となる者どもを　これから排除いたします
Now we get rid of them.
That is, do you advise me to quit Narsusa and Daryuna.
つまり　お主は私にナルサスやダリューンを捨てろというのだな
いかにも
Absolutely.
では聞くが　ダリューンやナルサスを私が捨てて　お主を選んだとして
Then I'll ask.
Suppose I leave Daryuna and Narsusa, will choose you,
今度はお主を捨てる日が来ないと　なぜ言い切れる
Where is the guarantee that one day you, too, as I did not give up?
You have told so much about Narsuse.
ナルサスの悪口をお主は言い立てる
だけど　ナルサスは
That's when he gave me shelter for the night
私に一夜の宿を与えておいて　だまし討ちなどしなかったぞ
and never secretly did not attack!
Stand before the angel of justice
問罪天使の前にまかり出て　生前の罪を告白するがいい
and confess their sins.
自分は裏切ってはならぬものを　全て裏切りましたとな
Admit it, how dare you betray it,
that he should not betray!
Mark, go. Now you are free.
さあ　行くがいい
お前たちはもう自由なのだから
ホディール様がそうおっしゃったのですか
So said Mr. Hodir?
ホディールは死んだ　だから…
Hodir dead.
Therefore...
あんたが殺したのか
You killed him?
私の仲間が…
One of my friends ...
なんだと
What?!
ご主人様の敵だ
Avenge the host!
I...
私は…
End!
やめろ
殿下
Prince!
待て
ナルサス　お主はこうなることが分かっていたのか
Narsus, you know what happens?
はい
Yes.
なぜ教えてくれなかったのだ
Why was not I told?
先にそう申し上げても　殿下は納得なさらなかったでしょう
Even if I had warned,
It would be unlikely to convince you it is.
世の中　経験せねば分からないこともあると思いましたので
I believe that in the world some things are better to learn from their own experience.
それはお主自身のことなのか
Are you talking about yourself?
Yes.
はい
５年前　亡くなった父の跡を継いだとき　私は奴隷を解放しました
Five years ago, when I inherited all after his father,
the freed slaves.
その後　王都に移っていたのですが
And then I went to the capital,
しばらくして　故郷に戻りますと
but when he came back,
奴隷たちが舞い戻っていたのです
servants reappeared.
なぜだ
Why?
寛大な主人の下に奴隷であることは　ある意味　最も楽な生き方なのです
Just being a slave to some wealthy owner easier.
だけど　お主は信念に基づいて正義を行ったのではないのか
But you did it, because he thought it right?
正義とは太陽ではなく　星のようなものかもしれません
Perhaps the best is considered not the sun and the stars.
星は天空に限りなくありますし　互いに光を打ち消し合います
The sky infinite number of stars,
and they interrupt each other shine.
Prince, in any case, do not let my words completely seize you.
殿下　なんにしても　私の申し上げることに左右なされますな
殿下は大道を歩もうとしておられる
You are trying to go in the right direction.
ぜひ　その道をお進みください
Please go to the very end.
この頼もしい５人が
These people are trustworthy ...
いつまでこうやって　自分についてきてくれるのだろうか
How far they will go with me?
彼らが愛想を尽かさないうちに
I must be worthy of the ruler as long as they are not disappointed in me.
自分は立派な君主にならなければならない
それで　夜が明けましたら　いずれの方角へおいでになりますか
So, soon the dawn where we are headed?
To the East. By fortress Peshavard!
東へ
ペシャワールへ向かう
Well, do not get stuck!
手を出すな
He killed my father and friends!
こいつはおやじと仲間の敵だ
Arslan group had to split up because of the chase.
追撃で分断されたアルスラーン一行
その渦中　ナルサスはゾット族の娘　アルフリードを救出する
Drawn into the fight, Narsus saves the Alfred, the leader of the clan daughter Zot.
Daughter of Commander Zot clan, the Alfred
Royal capital of Ecbatana
Kashan castle
Peshavard
その後　数々の包囲網をくぐり抜け　合流を果たした一行は
After avoiding the countless attempts to surround them,
group merged
パルス最大の戦力を残す東の拠点　ペシャワール城にたどり着いた
and finally arrived in the strongest fortress in the east, Peshavard,
which he remained most of the Parsis forces.
王太子殿下
Your Highness!
バフマン
Avalanches!
おお　よくぞ　ご無事で
Glad to see that you are alive.
Captain of Cavalry of the kingdom Pars, Kisvard
Captain of Cavalry of the kingdom Pars, Bahman
世話になるぞ　バフマン　キシュワード
We have to stop you, Bachmann, Kisvard.
パルスはこのペシャワールから　反撃ののろしを上げる
Pars will fight back from here in Peshawar.
みんなの力を貸してくれ
So I ask for your help!
はっ
There is!
ペシャワール城にある騎馬２万　歩兵６万挙げて
Twenty thousand horsemen and sixty thousand foot of the fortress of Peshawar
殿下に忠誠を誓わせていただきますぞ
will be honored for the privilege to serve you, Prince.
知らねばよかった
I wish I'd never known.
This burden is not for me.
知るべきではなかった
もし何もかも知らずにいられたなら
If it were possible to remain in ignorance,
I would have sworn eternal fidelity
あの聡明そうな王子に永遠の忠誠を誓うことができたであろう
this prince, who seems wise and prudent.
いま一度　問う
I ask again! Who are you?!
お主は何者だ
I am the son Osroesa, the previous king.
俺は先王オスロエスの子
ヒルメス
Hermes!
ペシャワール城に潜入した銀仮面卿ことヒルメスは　アルスラーンの命を狙う
Peshavard penetrated into the fortress,
Silver mask, known as Hermes, attacked Arslan.
彼を救ったのはアルスラーン出生の秘密を知るバフマンであった
And his defense stood Bachmann, who knew the secret of the birth of Arslan.
バフマンか
Avalanches ...
お懐かしゅうございます　ヒルメス殿下
Long time no see, Prince Hermes.
なぜ邪魔をした
Why are you prevented ?!
My friend asked ...
我が友の願いは…
アルスラーン殿下をお守りすること…
so I defended Prince Arslan.
待て
Stay!
If you kill him,
あのお方を殺せば　パルス王家の正当な血が絶えてしまう
legal race royal family Parsis interrupted it.
何を…
What do you...
よい王とおなりくだされ…
Please be a good king ...
バフマン
Avalanches!
アルスラーンとヒルメス
Lions e Hermes.
運命の嵐に翻弄される二人の王子が邂逅した
At the whim of fate itself
It took a chance encounter princes.
パルス暦３２０年　冬
The era of Pars, winter 320 years.
Despite the words of Bachman
バフマンの言葉が影を落とす中
new storm approaching sindoor under the face, the mighty east kingdom.
東方の大国　シンドゥラという新たな嵐が迫っていた
kimi ga deatta kokoro wa kitto
All the souls that you could meet on the way,
YakuSub Studio
hitotsu datte machigai janai
certainly it was pure and innocent,
translation Mu_Cool
onaji yume wo daite
We kept the same dream.
Editorial Mu_Cool
michi wo tagaeta hito wo omotta
People walking different paths,
nozarashi no akogare wo kakagete susumu kouya
killed all my hopes and desires revive again.
Making Helge
hohoemi mo sono namida mo
Smile on his face, tears running down her cheeks,
koko ni suteteyukenai kara
If you want to go ahead, they should not be forgotten.
kage wo daite shiroku takaku
Covered by the shadow of the summer, so white and immense,
namonaki boku to kimi no hata
our with you nameless flag flies.
mada hatenaku tsudzuku kono mich ino kanata ni
There, on the road, which extends an endless path,
tatta hitotsu no hikari wo sen no kokoro ni
There is one bright light, and with it a thousand souls.
miageru sora wo shinjiteru
Believe in the sky above his head,
michibiku hoshi wo higashi no takami ni sashishimesu yo
there putevodnaâ our star in the east, ee do not engage.
yume wa kono te de kanaeru
And their cherished dream in flesh forces.
ラジェンドラ王子は２４歳で
Rajendra prince of twenty-four,
パルスの王太子 アルスラーンより　ちょうど１０歳の年長である
that is, he is older than the Crown Prince Arslan Parsis ten years.
次回　異国の王子
Next time: "A foreign prince."
Chapter XIV
少年は そして王となる
And so the guy would be King.